<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Bioinformatics Institute Publications]]></title><description><![CDATA[Repository of all published Science Articles by our Researchers, their Group Members and Collaborators.]]></description><link>https://lumen.netlify.com</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2019 01:09:47 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[The dual interactions of p53 with MDM2 and p300: Implications for the design of MDM2 Inhibitors]]></title><description><![CDATA[Proteins that limit the activity of the tumour suppressor protein p53 are increasingly being targeted for inhibition in a variety of cancers. In addition to the development of small molecules, there has been interest in developing constrained (stapled) peptide inhibitors. A stapled peptide ALRN_6924 that activates p53 by preventing its interaction with its negative regulator Mdm2 has entered clinical trials.]]></description><link>https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-12-09-the-dual-interactions-of-p53-with-mdm2-and-p300-implications-for-the-design-of-mdm2-inhibitors/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-12-09-the-dual-interactions-of-p53-with-mdm2-and-p300-implications-for-the-design-of-mdm2-inhibitors/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2019 02:07:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Proteins that limit the activity of the tumour suppressor protein p53 are increasingly being targeted for inhibition in a variety of cancers. In addition to the development of small molecules, there has been interest in developing constrained (stapled) peptide inhibitors. A stapled peptide ALRN&lt;em&gt;6924 that activates p53 by preventing its interaction with its negative regulator Mdm2 has entered clinical trials. This stapled peptide mimics the interaction of p53 with Mdm2. The chances that this peptide could bind to other proteins that may also interact with the Mdm2-binding region of p53 are high; one such protein is the CREB binding protein (CBP)/p300. It has been established that phosphorylated p53 is released from Mdm2 and binds to p300, orchestrating the transcriptional program. We investigate whether molecules such as ALRN&lt;/em&gt;6924 would bind to p300 and, to do so, we used molecular simulations to explore the binding of ATSP&lt;em&gt;7041, which is an analogue of ALRN&lt;/em&gt;6924. Our study shows that ATSP_7041 preferentially binds to Mdm2 over p300; however, upon phosphorylation, it appears to have a higher affinity for p300. This could result in attenuation of the amount of free p300 available for interacting with p53, and hence reduce its transcriptional efficacy. Our study highlights the importance of assessing off-target effects of peptide inhibitors, particularly guided by the understanding of the networks of protein-protein interactions (PPIs) that are being targeted.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Utility of In Vitro Bioactivity as a Lower Bound Estimate of In Vivo Adverse Effect Levels and in Risk-Based Prioritization]]></title><description><![CDATA[Use of high-throughput, in vitro bioactivity data in setting a point-of-departure (POD) has the potential to accelerate the pace of human health safety evaluation by informing screening level assessments. The primary objective of this work was to compare PODs based on high-throughput predictions of bioactivity, exposure predictions, and traditional hazard information for 448 chemicals. ]]></description><link>https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-11-26-utility-of-in-vitro-bioactivity-as-a-lower-bound-estimate-of-in-vivo-adverse-effect-levels-and-in-risk-based-prioritization/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-11-26-utility-of-in-vitro-bioactivity-as-a-lower-bound-estimate-of-in-vivo-adverse-effect-levels-and-in-risk-based-prioritization/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2019 08:54:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Use of high-throughput, in vitro bioactivity data in setting a point-of-departure (POD) has the potential to accelerate the pace of human health safety evaluation by informing screening level assessments. The primary objective of this work was to compare PODs based on high-throughput predictions of bioactivity, exposure predictions, and traditional hazard information for 448 chemicals. PODs derived from new approach methodologies (NAMs) were obtained for this comparison using the 50th (PODNAM,50) and the 95th (PODNAM,95) percentile credible interval estimates for the steady-state plasma concentration used in in vitro to in vivo extrapolation of administered equivalent doses (AEDs). Of the 448 substances, 89% had a PODNAM,95 that was less than the traditional POD (PODtraditional) value. For the 48 substances for which PODtraditional &amp;#x3C; PODNAM,95, the PODNAM and PODtraditional were typically within a factor of 10 of each other, and there was an enrichment of chemical structural features associated with organophosphate and carbamate insecticides. When PODtraditional &amp;#x3C; PODNAM,95, it did not appear to result from an enrichment of PODtraditional based on a particular study type, (e.g. developmental, reproductive, chronic studies). Bioactivity:exposure ratios (BERs), useful for identification of substances with potential priority, demonstrated that high-throughput exposure predictions were greater than the PODNAM,95 for 11 substances. When compared to threshold of toxicological concern (TTC) values, the PODNAM,95 was greater than the corresponding TTC value 90% of the time. This work demonstrates the feasibility, and continuing challenges, of using in vitro bioactivity as a protective estimate of POD in screening level assessments via a case study.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Knockout of the non-essential gene SUGCT creates diet-linked, age-related microbiome disbalance with a diabetes-like metabolic syndrome phenotype]]></title><description><![CDATA[SUGCT (C7orf10) is a mitochondrial enzyme that synthesizes glutaryl-CoA from glutarate in tryptophan and lysine catabolism, but it has not been studied in vivo. Although mutations in Sugct lead to Glutaric Aciduria Type 3 disease in humans, patients remain largely asymptomatic despite high levels of glutarate in the urine. To study the disease mechanism, we generated SugctKO mice and uncovered imbalanced lipid and acylcarnitine metabolism in kidney in addition to changes in the gut microbiome. ]]></description><link>https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-11-26-knockout-of-the-non-essential-gene-sugct-creates-diet-linked-age-related-microbiome-disbalance-with-a-diabetes-like-metabolic-syndrome-phenotype/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-11-26-knockout-of-the-non-essential-gene-sugct-creates-diet-linked-age-related-microbiome-disbalance-with-a-diabetes-like-metabolic-syndrome-phenotype/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2019 08:11:42 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;SUGCT (C7orf10) is a mitochondrial enzyme that synthesizes glutaryl-CoA from glutarate in tryptophan and lysine catabolism, but it has not been studied in vivo. Although mutations in Sugct lead to Glutaric Aciduria Type 3 disease in humans, patients remain largely asymptomatic despite high levels of glutarate in the urine. To study the disease mechanism, we generated SugctKO mice and uncovered imbalanced lipid and acylcarnitine metabolism in kidney in addition to changes in the gut microbiome. After SugctKO mice were treated with antibiotics, metabolites were comparable to WT, indicating that the microbiome affects metabolism in SugctKO mice. SUGCT loss of function contributes to gut microbiota dysbiosis, leading to age-dependent pathological changes in kidney, liver, and adipose tissue. This is associated with an obesity-related phenotype that is accompanied by lipid accumulation in kidney and liver, as well as “crown-like” structures in adipocytes. Furthermore, we show that the SugctKO kidney pathology is accelerated and exacerbated by a high-lysine diet. Our study highlights the importance of non-essential genes with no readily detectable early phenotype, but with substantial contributions to the development of age-related pathologies, which result from an interplay between genetic background, microbiome, and diet in the health of mammals.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[G Protein–Coupled Receptors in Asthma Therapy: Pharmacology and Drug Action]]></title><description><![CDATA[Asthma is a heterogeneous inflammatory disease of the airways that is associated with airway hyperresponsiveness and airflow limitation. Although asthma was once simply categorized as atopic or nonatopic, emerging analyses over the last few decades have revealed a variety of asthma endotypes that are attributed to numerous pathophysiological mechanisms. The classification of asthma by endotype is primarily routed in different profiles of airway inflammation that contribute to bronchoconstriction. ]]></description><link>https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-11-26-g-protein–coupled-receptors-in-asthma-therapy-pharmacology-and-drug-action/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-11-26-g-protein–coupled-receptors-in-asthma-therapy-pharmacology-and-drug-action/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 08:00:14 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Asthma is a heterogeneous inflammatory disease of the airways that is associated with airway hyperresponsiveness and airflow limitation. Although asthma was once simply categorized as atopic or nonatopic, emerging analyses over the last few decades have revealed a variety of asthma endotypes that are attributed to numerous pathophysiological mechanisms. The classification of asthma by endotype is primarily routed in different profiles of airway inflammation that contribute to bronchoconstriction. Many asthma therapeutics target G protein–coupled receptors (GPCRs), which either enhance bronchodilation or prevent bronchoconstriction. Short-acting and long-acting β2-agonists are widely used bronchodilators that signal through the activation of the β2-adrenergic receptor. Short-acting and long-acting antagonists of muscarinic acetylcholine receptors are used to reduce bronchoconstriction by blocking the action of acetylcholine. Leukotriene antagonists that block the signaling of cysteinyl leukotriene receptor 1 are used as an add-on therapy to reduce bronchoconstriction and inflammation induced by cysteinyl leukotrienes. A number of GPCR-targeting asthma drug candidates are also in different stages of development. Among them, antagonists of prostaglandin D2 receptor 2 have advanced into phase III clinical trials. Others, including antagonists of the adenosine A2B receptor and the histamine H4 receptor, are in early stages of clinical investigation. In the past decade, significant research advancements in pharmacology, cell biology, structural biology, and molecular physiology have greatly deepened our understanding of the therapeutic roles of GPCRs in asthma and drug action on these GPCRs. This review summarizes our current understanding of GPCR signaling and pharmacology in the context of asthma treatment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SIGNIFICANCE STATEMENT Although current treatment methods for asthma are effective for a majority of asthma patients, there are still a large number of patients with poorly controlled asthma who may experience asthma exacerbations. This review summarizes current asthma treatment methods and our understanding of signaling and pharmacology of G protein–coupled receptors (GPCRs) in asthma therapy, and discusses controversies regarding the use of GPCR drugs and new opportunities in developing GPCR-targeting therapeutics for the treatment of asthma.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Linker length affects photostability of protein-targeted sensor of cellular microviscosity]]></title><description><![CDATA[Viscosity sensitive fluorophores termed 'molecular rotors' represent a convenient and quantitative tool for measuring intracellular viscosity via Fluorescence Lifetime Imaging Microscopy (FLIM). We compare the FLIM performance of two BODIPY-based molecular rotors bound to HaloTag protein expressed in different subcellular locations. ]]></description><link>https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-10-31-linker-length-affects-photostability-of-protein-targeted-sensor-of-cellular-microviscosity/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-10-31-linker-length-affects-photostability-of-protein-targeted-sensor-of-cellular-microviscosity/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2019 09:08:56 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Viscosity sensitive fluorophores termed ‘molecular rotors’ represent a convenient and quantitative tool for measuring intracellular viscosity via Fluorescence Lifetime Imaging Microscopy (FLIM). We compare the FLIM performance of two BODIPY-based molecular rotors bound to HaloTag protein expressed in different subcellular locations. While both rotors are able to penetrate live cells and specifically label the desired intracellular location, we found that the rotor with a longer HaloTag protein recognition motif was significantly affected by photo-induced damage when bound to the HaloTag protein, while the other dye showed no changes upon irradiation. Molecular dynamics modelling indicates that the irradiation-induced electron transfer between the BODIPY moiety and the HaloTag protein is a plausible explanation for these photostability issues. Our results demonstrate that binding to the targeted protein may significantly alter the photophysical behaviour of a fluorescent probe and therefore its thorough characterisation in the protein bound form is essential prior to any in vitro and in cellulo applications.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Rare Human Missense Variants can affect the Function of Disease-Relevant Proteins by Loss and Gain of Peroxisomal Targeting Motifs]]></title><description><![CDATA[Single nucleotide variants (SNVs) resulting in amino acid substitutions (i.e., missense variants) can affect protein localization by changing or creating new targeting signals. Here, we studied the potential of naturally occurring SNVs from the Genome Aggregation Database (gnomAD) to result in the loss of an existing peroxisomal targeting signal 1 (PTS1) or gain of a novel PTS1 leading to mistargeting of cytosolic proteins to peroxisomes.]]></description><link>https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-10-30-rare-human-missense-variants-can-affect-the-function-of-disease-relevant-proteins-by-loss-and-gain-of-peroxisomal-targeting-motifs/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-10-30-rare-human-missense-variants-can-affect-the-function-of-disease-relevant-proteins-by-loss-and-gain-of-peroxisomal-targeting-motifs/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2019 08:44:34 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Single nucleotide variants (SNVs) resulting in amino acid substitutions (i.e., missense variants) can affect protein localization by changing or creating new targeting signals. Here, we studied the potential of naturally occurring SNVs from the Genome Aggregation Database (gnomAD) to result in the loss of an existing peroxisomal targeting signal 1 (PTS1) or gain of a novel PTS1 leading to mistargeting of cytosolic proteins to peroxisomes. Filtering down from 32,985 SNVs resulting in missense mutations within the C-terminal tripeptide of 23,064 human proteins, based on gene annotation data and computational prediction, we selected six SNVs for experimental testing of loss of function (LoF) of the PTS1 motif and five SNVs in cytosolic proteins for gain in PTS1-mediated peroxisome import (GoF). Experimental verification by immunofluorescence microscopy for subcellular localization and FRET affinity measurements for interaction with the receptor PEX5 demonstrated that five of the six predicted LoF SNVs resulted in loss of the PTS1 motif while three of five predicted GoF SNVs resulted in de novo PTS1 generation. Overall, we showed that a complementary approach incorporating bioinformatics methods and experimental testing was successful in identifying SNVs capable of altering peroxisome protein import, which may have implications in human disease.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Large-Scale Whole-Genome Sequencing of Three Diverse Asian Populations in Singapore]]></title><description><![CDATA[Underrepresentation of Asian genomes has hindered population and medical genetics research on Asians, leading to population disparities in precision medicine. By whole-genome sequencing of 4,810 Singapore Chinese, Malays, and Indians, we found 98.3 million SNPs and small insertions or deletions, over half of which are novel. Population structure analysis demonstrated great representation of Asian genetic diversity by three ethnicities in Singapore and revealed a Malay-related novel ancestry component.]]></description><link>https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-12-09-large-scale-whole-genome-sequencing-of-three-diverse-asian-populations-in-singapore/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-12-09-large-scale-whole-genome-sequencing-of-three-diverse-asian-populations-in-singapore/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2019 02:19:01 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Underrepresentation of Asian genomes has hindered population and medical genetics research on Asians, leading to population disparities in precision medicine. By whole-genome sequencing of 4,810 Singapore Chinese, Malays, and Indians, we found 98.3 million SNPs and small insertions or deletions, over half of which are novel. Population structure analysis demonstrated great representation of Asian genetic diversity by three ethnicities in Singapore and revealed a Malay-related novel ancestry component. Furthermore, demographic inference suggested that Malays split from Chinese ∼24,800 years ago and experienced significant admixture with East Asians ∼1,700 years ago, coinciding with the Austronesian expansion. Additionally, we identified 20 candidate loci for natural selection, 14 of which harbored robust associations with complex traits and diseases. Finally, we show that our data can substantially improve genotype imputation in diverse Asian and Oceanian populations. These results highlight the value of our data as a resource to empower human genetics discovery across broad geographic regions.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Large-Scale Whole-Genome Sequencing of Three Diverse Asian Populations in Singapore]]></title><description><![CDATA[Underrepresentation of Asian genomes has hindered population and  medical genetics research on Asians, leading to population disparities in precision medicine. By whole-genome sequencing of 4,810 Singapore Chinese, Malays, and Indians, we found 98.3 million SNPs and small insertions or deletions, over half of which  are novel. Population structure analysis demonstrated great representation of  Asian genetic diversity by three ethnicities in Singapore and revealed a  Malay-related novel ancestry component. ]]></description><link>https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-09-26-large-scale-whole-genome-sequencing-of-three-diverse-asian-populations-in-singapore/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-09-26-large-scale-whole-genome-sequencing-of-three-diverse-asian-populations-in-singapore/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2019 08:44:34 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Underrepresentation of Asian genomes has hindered population and medical genetics research on Asians, leading to population disparities in precision medicine. By whole-genome sequencing of 4,810 Singapore Chinese, Malays, and Indians, we found 98.3 million SNPs and small insertions or deletions,  over half of which are novel. Population structure analysis demonstrated great representation of Asian genetic diversity by three ethnicities in Singapore and revealed a Malay-related novel ancestry component. Furthermore, demographic inference suggested that Malays split from Chinese ∼24,800 years ago and experienced significant admixture with East Asians ∼1,700 years ago, coinciding with the Austronesian expansion. Additionally, we identified 20 candidate loci for natural selection, 14 of which harbored robust associations with complex traits and diseases. Finally, we show  that our data can substantially improve genotype imputation in diverse Asian and Oceanian populations. These results highlight the value of our data
as a resource to empower human genetics discovery across broad geographic regions.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[BRAF inhibitors promote intermediate BRAF(V600E) conformations and binary interactions with activated RAS]]></title><description><![CDATA[Oncogenic BRAF mutations initiate tumor formation by unleashing the autoinhibited kinase conformation and promoting RAS-decoupled proliferative RAF-MEK-ERK signaling. We have engineered luciferase-based biosensors to systematically track full-length BRAF conformations and interactions affected by tumorigenic kinase mutations and GTP loading of RAS. ]]></description><link>https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-12-09-braf-inhibitors-promote-intermediate-braf-v600e-conformations-and-binary-interactions-with-activated-ras/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-12-09-braf-inhibitors-promote-intermediate-braf-v600e-conformations-and-binary-interactions-with-activated-ras/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2019 10:02:16 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Oncogenic BRAF mutations initiate tumor formation by unleashing the autoinhibited kinase conformation and promoting RAS-decoupled proliferative RAF-MEK-ERK signaling. We have engineered luciferase-based biosensors to systematically track full-length BRAF conformations and interactions affected by tumorigenic kinase mutations and GTP loading of RAS. Binding of structurally diverse αC-helix-OUT BRAF inhibitors (BRAFi) showed differences in specificity and efficacy by shifting patient mutation–containing BRAF reporters from the definitive opened to more closed conformations. Unexpectedly, BRAFi engagement with the catalytic pocket of V600E-mutated BRAF stabilized an intermediate and inactive kinase conformation that enhanced binary RAS:RAF interactions, also independently of RAF dimerization in melanoma cells. We present evidence that the interference with RAS interactions and nanoclustering antagonizes the sequential formation of drug-induced RAS:RAF tetramers. This suggests a previously unappreciated allosteric effect of anticancer drug-driven intramolecular communication between the kinase and RAS-binding domains of mutated BRAF, which may further promote paradoxical kinase activation and drug resistance mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Characterization of Hydration Properties in Structural Ensembles of Biomolecules]]></title><description><![CDATA[Solute-solvent interactions are critical for biomolecular stability and recognition.  Explicit solvent molecular dynamics (MD) simulations are routinely used to probe such  interactions. However, detailed analyses and interpretation of the hydration patterns  seen in MD simulations can be both complex and time-consuming.]]></description><link>https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-05-29-characterization-of-hydration-properties-in-structural-ensembles-of-biomolecules/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-05-29-characterization-of-hydration-properties-in-structural-ensembles-of-biomolecules/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2019 08:44:34 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Solute-solvent interactions are critical for biomolecular stability and recognition. Explicit solvent molecular dynamics (MD) simulations are routinely used to probe such interactions. However, detailed analyses and interpretation of the hydration patterns seen in MD simulations can be both complex and time-consuming. A variety of approaches/tools to compute and interrogate hydration properties in structural ensembles of proteins, nucleic acids, or in general any molecule are available and are complemented here with a new and free software package (“JAL”). Central to “JAL” is an intuitive atom centric approach of computing hydration properties. In addition to the standard metrics commonly used to understand hydration, “JAL” introduces two nonstandard utilities: a program to rapidly compute buried waters in an MD trajectory and a new method to compute multiwater bridges around a solute. We demonstrate the utility of the package by probing the hydration characteristics of the tumor suppressor protein p53 and the translation initiation factor eif4E. “JAL” is hosted online and can be accessed for free at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mspc.bii.a-star.edu.sg/minhn/jal.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;http://mspc.bii.a-star.edu.sg/minhn/jal.html&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Three-dimensional structure of Megabalanus rosa Cement Protein 20 revealed by multi-dimensional NMR and molecular dynamics simulations]]></title><description><![CDATA[Barnacles employ a protein-based cement to firmly attach to immersed substrates.  The cement proteins (CPs) have previously been identified and sequenced. However,  the molecular mechanisms of adhesion are not well understood, in particular,  because the three-dimensional molecular structure of CPs remained unknown to date.  Here, we conducted multi-dimensional nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) studies and  molecular dynamics (MD) simulations of recombinant Megabalanus rosa Cement Protein  20 (rMrCP20). ]]></description><link>https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-09-17-three-dimensional-structure-of-megabalanus-rosa-cement-proetin-20-reveled-by-multi-dimnesional-nmr-and-molecular-dynamics-simulations/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-09-17-three-dimensional-structure-of-megabalanus-rosa-cement-proetin-20-reveled-by-multi-dimnesional-nmr-and-molecular-dynamics-simulations/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2019 08:44:34 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt; Barnacles employ a protein-based cement to firmly attach to immersed substrates. The cement proteins (CPs) have previously been identified and sequenced. However, the molecular mechanisms of adhesion are not well understood, in particular, because the three-dimensional molecular structure of CPs remained unknown to date. Here, we conducted multi-dimensional nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) studies and molecular dynamics (MD) simulations of recombinant Megabalanus rosa Cement Protein 20 (rMrCP20). Our NMR results show that rMrCP20 contains three main folded domain regions intervened by two dynamic loops, resulting in multiple protein conformations that exist in equilibrium. We found that 12 out of 32 Cys in the sequence engage in disulfide bonds that stabilize the β-sheet domains owing to their placement at the extremities of β-strands. Another feature unveiled by NMR is the location of basic residues in turn regions that are exposed to the solvent, playing an important role for intermolecular contact with negatively charged surfaces. MD simulations highlight a highly stable and conserved β-motif (β7-β8), which may function as nuclei for amyloid-like nanofibrils previously observed in the cured adhesive cement. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first report describing the tertiary structure of an extracellular biological adhesive protein at the molecular level.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Molecular basis of dengue virus serotype 2 morphological switch from 29°C to 37°C]]></title><description><![CDATA[The ability of DENV2 to display different morphologies (hence different antigenic properties) complicates vaccine and therapeutics development. Previous studies  showed most strains of laboratory adapted DENV2 particles changed from smooth to  "bumpy" surfaced morphology when the temperature is switched from 29°C at 37°C.  ]]></description><link>https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-11-01-molecular-basis-of-dengue-virus-serotype-2-morphological-switch-from-29°C-to-37°C/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-11-01-molecular-basis-of-dengue-virus-serotype-2-morphological-switch-from-29°C-to-37°C/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 08:44:34 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;  The ability of DENV2 to display different morphologies (hence different antigenic properties) complicates vaccine and therapeutics development.  Previous studies showed most strains of laboratory adapted DENV2 particles changed from smooth to “bumpy” surfaced morphology when the temperature
is switched from 29°C at 37°C. Here we identified five envelope (E) protein residues different between two alternative passage history DENV2 NGC  strains exhibiting smooth or bumpy surface morphologies. Several mutations performed on the smooth DENV2 infectious clone destabilized the surface,  as observed by cryoEM. Molecular dynamics simulations demonstrated how chemically subtle substitution at various positions destabilized dimeric  interactions between E proteins. In contrast, three out of four DENV2 clinical isolates showed a smooth surface morphology at 37°C, and only at high fever temperature (40°C) did they become “bumpy”. These results imply vaccines should contain particles representing both morphologies. For   prophylactic and therapeutic treatments, this study also informs on which types of antibodies should be used at different stages of an infection, i.e., those that bind to monomeric E proteins on the bumpy surface or across multiple E proteins on the smooth surfaced virus.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Influenza A Hemagglutinin Passage Bias Sites and Host Specificity Mutations]]></title><description><![CDATA[Animal studies aimed at understanding influenza virus mutations that change host specificity to adapt to replication in mammalian hosts are necessarily limited in sample numbers due to high cost and safety requirements. As a safe, higher-throughput alternative, we explore the possibility of using readily available passage bias data obtained mostly from seasonal H1 and H3 influenza strains that were differentially grown in mammalian (MDCK) and avian cells (eggs). ]]></description><link>https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-11-01-influenza-a-hemagglutinin-passage-bias-sites-and-host-specificity-mutations/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://lumen.netlify.com/posts/2019-11-01-influenza-a-hemagglutinin-passage-bias-sites-and-host-specificity-mutations/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2018 08:46:28 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Animal studies aimed at understanding influenza virus mutations that change host specificity to adapt to replication in mammalian hosts are necessarily limited in sample numbers due to high cost and safety requirements. As a safe, higher-throughput alternative, we explore the possibility of using readily available passage bias data obtained mostly from seasonal H1 and H3 influenza strains that were differentially grown in mammalian (MDCK) and avian cells (eggs). Using a statistical approach over 80,000 influenza hemagglutinin sequences with passage information, we found that passage bias sites are most commonly found in three regions: (i) the globular head domain around the receptor binding site, (ii) the region that undergoes pH-dependent structural changes and (iii) the unstructured N-terminal region harbouring the signal peptide. Passage bias sites were consistent among different passage cell types as well as between influenza A subtypes. We also find epistatic interactions of site pairs supporting the notion of host-specific dependency of mutations on virus genomic background. The sites identified from our large-scale sequence analysis substantially overlap with known host adaptation sites in the WHO H5N1 genetic changes inventory suggesting information from passage bias can provide candidate sites for host specificity changes to aid in risk assessment for emerging strains.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>